Guide to the Girolamo Valenti Papers TAM.040
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Girolamo Valenti Papers
1925-1977, (Bulk 1930-1958)
1930-1958
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Valenti, Girolamo
Valenti, Sylvia
TAM.040
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Girolamo Valenti (1892-1958) was an anti-Fascist, anti-Communist editor, socialist, and labor leader who emigrated to the United States from Italy in 1911. The papers include correspondence, radio scripts, manuscripts, clippings and obituaries, the majority in Italian, relating to labor and political issues concerning Italy and Italian Americans.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Girolamo Valenti was an anti-Fascist, anti-Communist socialist, editor, and labor leader. Born April 16, 1892 in Valguarnera, Italy, he immigrated to the United States in 1911. He helped organize the Italian Socialist Federation (1913-1916), the Italian Chamber of Labor (1920-1921) and was active in the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (1916-1917). He edited Avanti, the organ of the Italian Socialist Federation (1917-1919), La Folla (1919-1920), La Parola del Popolo, organ of the Italian Socialist Federation of the Socialist Party (ca. 1921- ca.1948), and Il Nuovo Mondo and its successor La Stampa Libera, liberal dailies (ca. 1925 – 1940s). During World War II he consulted for the OSS (Office of Strategic Services), and in the post-war years, he was an Italian-language radio commentator whose programs were broadcast in New York, several other U.S. cities, and in Italy. He wrote several pamphlets concerning socialism and participated in socialist campaigns and strikes. He was a member of the Socialist Party, and a leader of the Circolo Matteotti, an anti-fascist organization. He died in New York City on February 20, 1958.
Scope and Content Note
The papers include correspondence, radio scripts, manuscripts (article-length), clippings and obituaries, the majority in Italian, relating to labor and political issues concerning Italy and Italian Americans, and to his radio career. Among the letters are two from Estelle Sylvia Pankhurst regarding Circolo Matteotti, and a few letters each from Velia Matteotti, Pietro Nenni, Count Carlo Sforza, and Ignazio Silone. Included are scripts from Italian language radio shows on current events that were broadcast on WOV (New York), WHNC (New Haven, Connecticut), Italy, and elsewhere; a file containing obituaries and other biographical portraits, material on the Pope Affair, and letters to Valenti's wife, Sylvia, after his death, including several from Norman Thomas.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
Container list.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Sylvia Valenti in 1965. The accession number associated with this gift is 1965.002. Typescripts by Sylvia Valenti were found in repository in April of 2014 and were added to this collection. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.081.
Separated Materials
Photographs were separated from this collection during initial processing and were established as a separate collection, the Girolamo Valenti Photographs (PHOTOS 039).
Obituaries.; Manuscripts for publication.; Radio scripts.; Socialists -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Anti-fascist movements -- United States.; Italian American labor leaders.; Italian American newspaper editors.; Italian American socialists.; Italian Americans; Correspondence.; Matteotti, Velia, 1890-1938; Pankhurst, E. Sylvia (Estelle Sylvia), 1882-1960.; Nenni, Pietro, 1891-1980.; Sforza, Carlo, conte, 1872-1952; Pope, Generoso.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Silone, Ignazio, 1900-1978; Valenti, Sylvia; WHNC (Radio station: New Haven, Conn.); WOV (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); Circolo Matteotti; Valenti, Sylvia
- Container list
  - Bibliography: Valenti Writings in Newspapers, 1933-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical (includes John Nicholas Beffel notes and Sylvia Valenti Writings), 1956-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carl Tresca Memorial Meeting: Flier, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Clippings (Mainly Italian), 1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Condolences, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Matteotti, Velia, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Nenni, Pietro, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Pankhurst, Sylvia, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Sforza, Carlo, 1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Silone, Ignazio, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Valenti, Sylvia, 1958-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Fascist Propaganda in the United States" (Typescript), Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Giovannitti, Arturo, 1942-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Obituaries, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pope Affair: Clippings from Il Progresso Italo-Americano, 1955-1957, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pope Affair: Fascism, Anti-Semitism Rampant in Editorial Room of "Il Progresso Italo-Americano," An Open Letter to its Editor and Publisher Fortune R. Pope [Girolamo Valenti]; also includes "The Story of the Pamphlet," by Sylvia Valenti, c.1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pope Affair: General, c.1941-1958, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Radio Programs, 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Radio Programs, 1955-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Radio Programs, 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Radio Programs, 1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbooks, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Socialist Party: Flier (in Italian), undated (Box 2, Folder 6a)
  - Writings, Manuscripts & Typescripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings, Published (articles & pamphlets), 1920, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sylvia Valenti Writings (The Journey A-Cross, The $50 Psychiatrist, personal notes), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)